Never forget why you are the church.
So we're back in Romans this morning, as we celebrate Cedar
Grove, turning 213 years old this past Friday.
We call this Vision Day, Vision Sunday,
and I want to just pause just to let that settle in.
Sometimes I feel like we go to church, and we
kind of go through the motions just like we sang about just then,
and we don't realize exactly what we are truly a part of.
And for the last 213 years, believers
have gathered on this hill in order to stir
up each other's gifts.
And just like we said, provoke one another to serving
God in good works, to put in perspective just how long,
Cedar Grove has been around.
Let me give you some facts about the history here.
Our 1st pastor, pastor was Elijah Maddox.
I believe he was here in Miss Virginia.
She's our historian, so she could correct me on this, but I think it was around 24
years as pastor.
I could be wrong about that.
But he was born in 1773.
That's pretty old, amen?
I mean, that's like a 17.
That's that's crazy.
December of that same year is
when the Boston Tea Party happened where the Sons of Liberty dumped
92,000 pounds of tea in the Harvard protesting
the new tax act.
In 1813, when this church was formed,
the Allies defeated Napoleon.
James
Madison was serving his first term.
This church has seen 42 sitting U.S. presidents.
We haven't had too many more than that.
To get to church,
Well, let me say this, the population of Tennessee at
that time was roughly 400,000.
Today, in Tennessee, there is roughly 7.4
million, and you know, there's a million coming every month, you
know, in the Wilson County, so it's gonna just go up from there.
Uh, to get,
uh, the church has seen, our nation has seen, since
the church has started, roughly 10 to 12 major
wars.
To get the church, our founding
members primarily walked or rode horseback.
Luxury travel was stagecoach that averaged 4 miles per hour.
Y'all would miss church, let me just tell you.
Ain't no way y'all getting here.
Mercy.
As a
matter of fact, when that cedar tree fell down.
I don't know if you know, but there was 3 cedar trees in the storm, it took one of them.
We wanted to kind of do something with it, but
we realized there's so many nails and so many things where they actually
posted up their horse and stuff to sit
out there while they were coming in to church.
So that's just a pretty cool history right there.
You're sitting in just the 3rd house of worship
that has sat on this hill in that amount of time.
Just the 3rd house of worship.
Church, God has blessed Cedar Grove Baptist Church.
With a range of 4000 to
10,000 local churches closing its doors permanently every single year.
Let me repeat that just to give you some perspective.
4000 of 10,000 churches.
Every single year, close their doors permanently,
no longer do people gather there in the name of Jesus to worship him.
It is it
is no small deal that we have been here and kept ministry going
for 213 years.
That is why Vision Day is so important.
We know our mission here,
our purpose is, the reason we exist.
We already went over, but love others unconditionally, learn about God increasingly,
live to share Jesus intentionally and lead others to Christ continually
in Lebanon, Tennessee, and throughout the whole world.
That is the mission.
That is what we are here to do.
The vision of this church is where we are trying to get to.
See, the mission gets us to the vision.
So what is our vision?
Well, really our vision, and I don't have a little nice little
cute little saying for it, but our vision should be no different than
every other biblical New Testament church.
We want to see as many people saved,
and as many people saved people, disciple closer
to Christ as possible in our sphere of influences.
If we keep this at the forefront of our hearts
and minds, we will continue to be a close family in this church.
We will continue to impact the community.
We will continue to see people walk with Christ closer.
We will continue to see victory after victory here.
By the way, I just want to kind of say
this, I know that we're in an area of growth.
Trust me, if you look around and see ceases because we are getting closer and
closer to summer, you know, tennis is not
always good and summer, people like to go and do and travel and
all things, and I get that, but we are in a season of growth here.
And so many people, listen, I've heard and
genuine, sincere, authentic.
They love the Lord.
They love this church, but their biggest fear is, I
don't want this church to grow to a certain point to where we don't have what we have now.
The
issue with that is this.
If we're not grown, we're dying.
It's just a simple fact.
And I don't necessarily mean a number like crazy.
There's a lot of different ways that a church is supposed to grow.
But here's the thing.
I can tell you how we prevent that from happening
at Cedar Grove.
If you want to prevent from being that big church that you go in,
you hide in a pew somewhere, you leave without saying hi
and buy to anybody there, right?
You got a lot of people, big budget, but there's no family field.
You know how you prevent that?
You start a culture now of serving Christ together.
That's what you do.
Listen, if every single one of us today had
a job and a role to do here at this local church.
And when people come in, they realize, whoa, hold on.
They were sitting beside me last week, but they're not here this week.
You know why?
They're helping with the children.
Well, hold on, the person in front of me, they haven't
been here for 2 weeks in a row, what are they doing?
Oh, well, they're helping with the students.
They're helping a nursery.
When we start creating that culture.
Guess what?
People are either gonna stay or leave.
But if they stay, they're gonna serve.
Y'all with me?
y'all with me?
You understand what I'm saying this morning?
So listen, we don't want to fear growth.
But I understand.
I like what we got going on here.
I was just talking to Taylor and Bre.
We were talking about how at 21 years old.
I got voted in.
I was 3 months into my 21st year, you understand?
And literally, the miracle is that 10
years later, just about, we're still doing this.
I love what God has done here.
I love the fact that I know y'all.
I love the fact the biggest compliment
I've ever gotten, okay, from somebody that does not
go to this church, we were having our real momentum
meeting with Keith Boggs.
And when I, there was all the name tags
laid out on the table.
And I started just kind of talking about what people were going through
to Keith and we were just kind of, you know, praying through and stuff.
And when we got done, Keith looked at me and said, man, you really know your people.
And I said, well, that's my job.
That's how you shepherd a flock.
listen, we don't want to lose that here.
But we also want to push forward.
We don't want to stay where we are.
We also want to continue to
serve him like we're serving.
So the ultimate goal is to magnify the ministry here at Cedar Grove.
Why?
So the name of Jesus can be magnified.
Look at what Paul says about this in Romans 11,
verse 13 through 15, but I am speaking to you who are Gentiles, inasmuch
then as I am an apostle of Gentiles.
I magnify my ministry.
If somehow I might move the jealousy, my fellow
countrymen, and save some of them.
For if their rejection is the reconciliation of the world,
What will their acceptance be, but life and the dead?
Now, we went in extensive Bible study on that text.
I'm not going to preach it again, but Paul knew that
the more his ministry for Jesus was magnified.
The more he reached the Gentiles, he understood
that those that were seeing people's lives changed according
to the gospel, and through Jesus Christ.
It was gonna provoke those who were lost to jealousy and want to be a part of that.
We get so outwardly thinking sometimes
that we forget that what's going on here.
The best way to serve the community,
the best way to show the community that God's doing something here is
to serve each other in love, to be designated
and dedicated to each other, to live life together in faith.
That is going to provoke others to come.
But we say, well, you know, if we don't if
we don't grow here, grow there, or I just want to invite people to church, hey, the best invite
is to show what God is doing in your life.
We ought not be ashamed of growth.
We ought not be hesitant on our online presence.
We need to see the modern tools, not as negative, but
rather a way to get the gospel to do more in our community.
I have a question for you today.
Do you love and enjoy what God is doing at Cedar Grove Baptist Church right now.
Say, amen if you do.
If you don't get out.
No, I'm just kidding.
That's the old Jacob.
Amen?
But no, listen, amen.
So be it.
We want this for every other person, too.
We cannot become complacent.
You must continue to push forward for Christ.
Now, what does any of this have to do at Romans 12.
And specifically the current theme of what we're
in, the impact of the gospel in ministry.
And if you want a caveat there, you can even add the word personal ministry and personal ministry.
Well, we're going over the spiritual grace gifts of Romans
12, and so far we have gone over 4 of them.
So if you look at Romans chapter 12, verse 6 through eight.
If you're there, say read.
Having then gifts differing according
to the grace that is given to us, whether prophecy, let
us prophecy according to the proportion of faith, or ministry,
let us wait on our ministry.
And that means serve.
So in serving, let us in our serving, or he that teacheth
on teaching, or he that exhorteth, that is encourage,
on encouragement.
Now this morning, we're going to move to the next gift mentioned here.
And listen, hey, I love when God works things out.
But our next gift is simply the gift of giving.
Look at Romans 12, verse 8, he that giveth,
let him do it with simplicity.
We're looking again at the impact of the gospel
and ministry.
in my ministry and your ministry and our ministry here at Cedar Grove.
Let's pray, Father, I thank you, Lord, for your word.
I thank you for this day.
And I thank you just for your faithfulness throughout the years.
We can literally say your faithfulness
throughout centuries, but we can even go further than that.
Your faithfulness since creation.
So God, I pray, Lord, that we do not pay for granted
in what you have done in our lives.
God, I pray that we do not take for granted the cloud of witnesses,
God, that is attached to this ministry here at this church.
So God, I pray that as I preach, I do so with
clarity, power, and liberty, and God pierce the hearts
that are here today.
And it's in Jesus name.
Anybody said?
Amen.
I want to 1st look at, we're going to look at 3 things about the gift of giving.
And we're going to look at number one, we're going to look at the principle of giving.
I like the clarity of the NSB 95 here.
It says this in verse 8, he who gives with liberality.
That means that we see that this is a generosity gift.
This is a grace gift that requires a
generous heart posture.
Now, I do want to make a point of clarification here.
There is a strong push against the biblical
principle, principle of the tithe.
Now, although the gift of giving
goes beyond what we would know as a regular tie
to a local church or if you want to call it the storehouse,
whatever your lingo you want to use, it is important to understand this tension.
Right?
By the way, there are too many people that are trying to look at
scripture to justify their apathy spiritually.
You understand what I'm saying?
So, in other words, if you look at scripture and you study scripture,
and you teach scripture, and the result is a lesser
walk with Christ, and not a greater walker
Christ, you need to re-look at scripture, this
is to get us closer with him, not further from him.
We don't justify our sin.
We don't justify our laziness.
We don't justify our non-attendance.
We don't justify anything that would take us away from his will for
our life with scripture.
That is, by definition, a false gospel.
Now, if you're here on Wednesday night, we call that the Spirit of the Antichrist,
okay, let's get serious about it.
But either way, listen, what does this mean here?
We sit here and we see the tension
between, well, should we tie, should we do this?
What does New Testament giving look like?
Well, see, a Jew in a New Testament period, if you look at
what they gave, they would actually get between 20 to 23%
of their increase.
No one ever talks about that.
No one ever said, it's always,
well, if you actually are comparing what we're doing now with
them, then you need to up your percentage.
Oh, y'all didn't like that, did you?
Okay.
I'm going to make y'all mad.
listen, we should have taken a love offer before we did this.
Amen.
Man, but either way, but listen,
so when people argue the fact that a tie does not commanded for
a New Testament church,
listen, they're not wrong.
But they typically do not understand the actual
laws regarding the people's tithes of that time.
As a matter of fact, Jesus rebukes sharply
the faithful tithers of that day because although
they were tithing, they were bankrupt in justice, mercy, and love.
So in other words, listen, your
giving must be paired with a heart
posture biblically walking with Christ here.
So what about the church then?
Are we the New Testament saints commanded to time?
Well, the answer is, and listen, there's a lot of pastors to disagree
with me, right?
And that's okay.
But the answer is no to the command.
However, this is not play in the favor of
those who are looking for reason not to give.
You say, what do you mean?
Remember, we're talking about generosity here.
We're talking about a grace gift that is founded upon
generosity.
How did the early church gear, because
remember, if we want to be a biblical New
Testament church, it'd probably be good to go look at the early New
Testament church in the Bible.
Amen.
Don't get much more biblical than that.
You see what I'm saying?
So how did the 1st church give?
How did that early church give?
If a tide was not commanded,
Surely they were not bound by such practices.
Well, you underestimate the response to grace.
they displayed.
Acts chapter 2, verse 40 through 47.
By the way, this is not highlighted, underlined, and notated
in your Bible.
Today's the day.
This is one of my favorite texts in all the Bible.
It says this and start in verse 40.
And with many other words, did he testify and exhort, saying, save
yourselves from this on toward generation.
And they that gladly receive his word, we're baptized.
And the same day, they were added unto them about 3000 souls.
3000 souls.
Some of y'all been like, eh, I don't know that person.
Well, guess what?
Look what they did right here.
And they continued steadfastly.
They continue steadfastly in the apostles'
doctrine and fellowship, and in breaking of bread,
and in prayers, and fear came upon every soul,
and many wonders and signs were done by the apostles.
And all that believed were together and
had all things common.
Look at verse 45 and sold their possessions
and goods and parted them to all men as every man had need.
And they continuing daily with one according to
temple and breaking bread from house to house, did eat their meat with
gladness and singleness of heart, praising God, and
having favor with all the people.
By the way, you want to see a testimony of a church?
Are you are you favored outside of this place?
Are you favored in here?
You understand what I'm saying?
Do people see you as a sour patch kid in here?
No, listen, so often we come here.
You do realize that in a restaurant business, the
worst crowd of the week is the Sunday crowd when they get out of church.
And
we are wondering while we're losing our influence.
Why, the Bible says that the 1st
church, they had favor with all people.
You know why?
Because the gospel, the grace they received,
it went out to everyone they came across.
Listen, you cannot be a mean,
bitter, unforgiven person outside of these walls
and expect God to use you like that.
That's a whole nother message.
I'm about to preach that soon.
But look at the result of this.
And the Lord added to the church daily.
Such as should be saved.
Don't miss the
practice of giving the early church had.
In verse 45, we got to stay focused here.
Look again, and sold their possessions and goods, and
part of them to all men as every man had made.
A
principle was set almost immediately when the
church was established, established.
That principle was generous giving.
There was no percentage.
There was no debate on how much.
It was all voluntary and out of a proper heart posture.
It is interesting to note that the
1st people we see recorded, that God himself killed was
in connection to their giving.
Look at Acts chapter 5.
We're going to read a lot of scripture today.
Is that okay with y'all?
If it's not, get out.
And I'm just kidding.
Stay.
But Acts chapter 5, verse one through 11.
But a certain man named Ananias, with Sapphira,
his wife sold a possession.
was starting off pretty good here, right?
We just saw in Acts 245.
That's what the church was doing.
But then look at verse 2 and kept back part of the price.
His wife also being privy to
it and brought a certain part and laid it at the apostle's feet.
But Peter said, Ananias, why has Satan
filled thine heart to lie to the Holy Ghost?
and to keep part of the price, keep back
part of the price of the land.
Whiles it remained, was it not thine own?
And after it was sold, was it not in thine own power?
Why hast thou conceived this thing in thine heart?
Thou hast not lied in the men, but in the God.
And Ananias, hearing these words fell down and gave up the ghost.
That means he dropped dead.
And great fear came on all of them that heard these things,
and a young man arose, wound them up and carried them out and buried him.
And it was about the space of 3 hours after when
his wife, not knowing what was done, came in, and Peter answered unto her,
tell me whether ye sold the land for so much, she said,
yes, for so much.
Then Peter said unto her, how is that you
have agreed together to tempt the spirit of the Lord.
Behold, the feet of them which have buried thy husband or
at the door and shall carry thee out.
Then fell she down straightway at his feet and yielded up the ghost.
In other words, she dropped dead as well.
And the young men came in and found her dead and carrying her forth
buried her by her husband.
And great fear came upon all the church, and upon as many as heard these things.
Now,
you're probably thinking, if that is not manipulative preaching right there,
I don't know what is.
But understand what Peter told her.
When you had the possession, was it not yours?
When
you sold it, was it not in your power what you made?
But you have chosen to lie to God.
In
other words, no one asked you to give this.
No one's
forcing you to make that donation.
No one no one is yes, the culture, the church, that's what we're doing.
And obviously it was so evident that in you, they had to do something.
It's kind of like when you come to church and you feel like, well, I've got to stand up
because everyone else is standing up or, well, I've got to say amen, because everyone else
is saying amen, or, well, I better go to that fellowship meal because everyone else is.
Listen, that's not why we do things.
We do things to glorify and honor the Lord.
And if that just so happens, brings us together, doing it all together, then so be it.
So notice the problem was not the amount,
but the mindset.
They wanted all the blessing of generous giving without
the actual generosity.
There was no ruler law that the
man of them that give all their profit, yet they decided to lie in order
to make themselves look more godly.
Two things I want to say about this happening.
First, this kind of generosity, again, was obviously expected and
practiced church wide, even though it was not commanded, else, why would they lie about it?
Second,
this exposed a tragic culture in the church.
People attend and enjoy the blessings of a local church
and its ministry, yet so often they are not as involved as they'd
like everyone to believe.
This
example of improper generosity is contrasted by what generosity should look like.
Before that, we see a picture of what generosity
looks like in Acts chapter 4, verse 32 through 37.
It says in the congregation, those who believe were of one heart and
soul, and not one of them claimed that anything belonging
to him was his own, but all things were common property to them.
And with great power, the apostles were given
testimony through the resurrection of the Lord Jesus, and abundant grace was upon them all.
For there was not a needy person among them,
for all who were owners of land or houses would sell them
and bring the proceeds of the sales.
And lay them at the apostles' feet, and they
would be distributed as each as any had need.
Now Joseph, a Levite, a Cyprian birth,
who was also called Barnabas.
You remember Barnabas?
By the apostles which translated
means son of encouragement, and
who owned a tract of land, sold it, and brought the money and laid it to the apostles' feet.
So we
see here that, obviously, Barnum would have the gift of encouragement and giving, but
this comes directly before the record of Ananias and Sapphira.
What does this have to do with the principle of giving, to limits
one generosity to a percentage was unheard of in the early church?
This debate that
we had today was not had.
Because they understood the scribes
and the Pharisees in the old ways.
And as a matter of fact, the Gentiles, they would have seen these
people as the religious elite and understood, man, that's a bunch of hypocrisy.
I don't want to give like that.
I wanna give better than that.
People all the time say, well,
I'm not under the law, preacher, so you can't put nothing on me.
Yet, you're under grace.
We have been elevated.
Our service, look, it should look different.
It looked different here in the early church.
They were genuinely living in faith.
They were the way they interlocked their faith, was to be in
one accord, not just spiritually, but in every way, financially, everything.
Preacher, are you asking me to sell my house and give the money to the church?
I sure am not.
I want you to have a place to live.
But here's the thing.
All I'm asking you to do is believe God's word.
Paul teaches us what amount we should give.
1st Corinthians 16, verse 2, upon the 1st day of the week,
let every one of you lay by him in store as God have
prospered him, that there be no gatherings when I come.
As God hath prospered him.
Does
your giving match your blessings?
What
I'm saying is that we need to stop trivializing what giving looks like in the church.
And by the way, we need to stop being so weird about money in the church.
While we worried about something that's his.
I've never gotten that.
And we'll talk about everything else.
Oh, but don't talk about my money.
Well, you have a theological error right there.
Listen,
do I tie 10%?
We sure do.
I would never ask you to do something that I'm not willing to.
And by the way, as a matter of fact, I'll go ahead and tell you, for
a long time, I would maybe
sometimes participate, sometimes not in love offerings, and this and
that, because I'm thinking, man, I'm doing all this, I'm doing all that.
I'm the one that got them in here, everything, all this stuff, you know, God convicted me of that.
As a matter
of fact, listen, and just to kind of give you a little glimpse, right?
2026 has been the year of spending for old Lanham family.
Let me just tell you, we got a 10 year anniversary.
We, you know, we're trying to go on a vacation.
We're doing all these things.
We're renovating the bonus room for our girls to,
you know, prepare for Roman to come in.
I mean, there was just a lot going on financially in my home.
So it was very easy in the back of my mind, you know what?
Well, I just, you know, we just can't do it.
And here's the thing.
It wasn't that we can't.
It was that I was worried that, hey, well, God, if I do, what if this happens?
What did that happen?
Let me just tell you something.
That's not how you give.
You give generously, you trust God with the rest.
By the way, he may not replenish it tenfold.
I wish he would.
Amen.
But he may not do that.
I'm not giving for that.
Today, especially.
I'm getting ahead of myself, but let's just sit here for a second.
Today, especially, you know what I'm giving towards?
You know what my family is giving towards, somebody having a seat to hear God's word.
If
I see someone sitting in a seat and give their life to the Lord.
You know what?
He's replenished me.
Oh, y'all with me this morning.
Come on now, let's not be weird.
I'm just asking you to believe God's word.
Does your giving match your blessing?
God does not own 10% of my money.
He owns it all.
We have to understand the principle of giving,
but there is also the purpose of giving.
The purpose of giving is laid out in Acts 2 and Acts 4.
In Acts 245 and sold their possessions and goods,
and part of them, the all men, as every man had need.
Acts 4, verse 35, and laid them down at the apostles' feet,
and distribution was made unto every man according as
he had need.
The early church was a family.
A community of believers who live in life together.
They serve Christ together.
In whatever context, their everyday life had.
They centered around Jesus and his followers.
There's nothing that says they didn't work.
There's nothing to say they didn't have kids.
There's nothing that said they didn't have hobbies, but all that was centered
around the family of God and Jesus.
I want you to notice something here, though.
Their outreach was the faith they had
that pierced every part of their life.
They lived a life of such generosity
of such love and of such faith that
it attracted people to Jesus.
This resulted in a huge group of
people that had various needs.
Therefore, the church made sure each was taken care of.
Now, I understand what you're thinking.
This is a radical church policy and procedures compared to the day.
Pretty sure it does sound like you're telling me to sell
my cars in my house and give and just all of us live in a little community and stuff.
No, no, no, no.
Don't misunderstand what I'm saying.
We have treated ministry to those in needs so
outwardly that we have turned the believers into
a bank account rather than a movement for Christ.
In other words, people look at a church.
Well, if you don't help this person over here on the street.
And if you don't help this person over here in this house, and if you don't help that
person, it comes and calls me every single time asking for money, then you're not a real church.
No, no, no, notice where the money and the help was going to them.
This
is radical, is it not?
Because our mindset is, oh, we gotta pay out.
We got to pay out.
We got to pay out, but we see here that the practice and the principle
and the purpose was the edification
in the building of the family of God.
And guess what happened?
Everyone noticed it.
Man, these people may have nothing, but they have everything.
That person there, man, that wealthy person.
We'll talk about a person of giving, but look at how they're
providing and even through the tough times,
they're together, they're serving, they're loving, they're giving.
I want to be a part of that.
How can I be a part of that?
Share the gospel, and add it daily.
that should be saved.
You
say, you telling me we should not supposed to help those people in the streets.
I'm telling you this.
I'm not saying we don't, we give to missions.
We get to the SBC cooperation.
We give to the Lottie moons and the, you know, the Annie Armstrongs.
We give to our community partners, and I'm not saying we stopped that.
But what I'm saying is we better
have the correct purpose of our giving.
is be
to build up what God is doing here.
People
will call it a church for not helping every single person who comes asking for money when
that person has no intentions of hearing the gospel to be a part of what God is doing.
Share them the gospel.
I can't tell you how many times someone has called and
said, hey, preacher, I just want you to know
I been calling everybody.
And I just, I can't pay my rent.
Can y'all help?
And I say, well, let me ask you, where do you go to church?
They don't have to go to church anywhere.
I'm just seeing if we can invite them.
It's not a it's not a test question.
It's just, hey, if you have a church family, if you call them, what's going on?
Oh, well, no, I'm looking for one.
Well, I know one.
I said, you know what?
You come on Sunday and we'll have a sit down talk.
Click.
Guys, I know this, listen, I was talking a lot of
day, uh, as I was preparing this and he was like, man, he's
like, this is going to be serious.
And listen, I get it.
This is not what we understand
as how we should operate as the church,
but every mention of giving in the context of the church was
to help and aid those within the church.
You know what this does?
This turns a person from simply writing a check every now and again into
someone who is investing in the kingdom and people of God who's right near them right there.
In other words, when we give,
I can say this, I'm giving to you.
I'm giving to the Lord, but I'm giving for you.
I'm giving for y'all.
See, I'm giving to my family.
We
got to stop saying, well, we give the keep the lights on and pay the staff.
Man, forget all that.
That's good.
That's great.
I glad you do.
Amen?
But we get for more than that.
Do
I believe in giving emissions?
Of course I do.
But the greatest mission we can invest in is sitting right here in this sanctuary.
And that's each other.
Our generosity is for the building of the church.
It is a grace gift, given primarily for the context of the
gathering of believers.
And to do this right takes a generous people.
By the way, speaking of people, this brings
us to our concluding portion this morning, and we're going to have to
move really fast here, but we've looked at the principle of giving, the purpose
of giving, but next we see the people of giving.
Throughout the Bible, both in the Old Testament New Testament, we see examples of generosity.
The Old Testament saints were blessed abundantly
and had no problem sharing and spreading their wealth to others.
In the New Testament, we see the church, whether rich or poor, give generously
to the benefit of one another, but there is a person in the Bible
whose gift of giving was evident to all who knew her, and her name is Lydia.
We get some details of this gifted
woman in Acts chapter 16, verse 11 through 15.
This is therefore, therefore, loosing from Troas,
we came with a straight course to Samarthrasia, and the next day
to Neapolis.
And from thence to Philippi, which is the chief city of that part of
Macedonia, and a colony, and we were in
that city abiding certain days.
So we're in Philippi right here.
And on the Sabbath, we went out of the city by a riverside,
where prayer was wont to be made, and we sat down and spake unto
the women which resorted hither.
And a certain woman named Lydia, a seller
of purple, of the city of Thiatira, which worshiped
God, heard us, whose heart the Lord opened,
that she attended unto the things which were spoken of Paul.
And when she was baptized in her household, she
besought us, saying, if ye have judged me to be faithful to the
Lord, come into my house and abide there, and she constrained us.
And there are some details about Lydia that I need to emphasize this morning.
We sit here that she was from the city of
Thyaterer when, and she was a seller of purple fabrics.
This was a business that would have brought in significant income.
Her being from that particular city,
actually, is important because that city was famous for
their indigo trade.
So, in other words, she was from somewhere where what she was doing was
very successful, and she was moving to Philippi to
continue and expand her business.
Lydia was a wealthy woman.
But she was in Philippi, no
doubt, trying to expand that.
So Paul shared the gospel with Lydia, by the way.
She was worshiping God.
She knew of God.
She was acknowledging a Sabbath.
She understood the religious stuff about it, but she did not truly
have a relationship with God.
So Paul preached the gospel.
She received the gospel.
She was baptized.
She said, come on in and prove
me if I'm true to this.
And obviously she was very hospitable
and very persuading because she constrained them.
But again, we
see that Lydia, just to kind of give you an idea, Lydia was
the 1st recorded convert in the area that we know today is Europe.
It is also understood
that Lydia used her home as the primary gathering place for the church that
was started in Philippi.
We see this in Acts 16,
It says this.
It says, and they went out of the prison.
Remember when they were in prison and they came back out and entered to the house of Lydia?
And when they had seen the brethren, they comforted them in the part.
In other words, they were gathered in Lydia's house.
Now that means that obviously she had enough house, she had enough home.
She had enough means to feed and to take care of
the entire church of that city.
And she did it.
Now, why is Philippi
so significant regarding giving?
Why is all this so,
so, so important?
Well, it was the church in Philippi that greatly helped Paul financially
in a time of need.
We're going to read a lot of scripture here and a lot of scripture that you know, but in
Philippians chapter 4, starting in verse 10, but
I rejoiced in the Lord greatly.
This is Paul's letter to the saints in a church in Philippi.
that now at the last, at the last, your care
of me hath flourished again.
In other words, they've cared for him before, they're caring
for him again, wherein you were also careful, but you lacked opportunity.
Now that I speak in respect of want, for I
have learned in whatsoever state I am, therewith to be content.
I know both how to be a base and how to abound everywhere
and in all things, I am instructed both to be full and to be hungry,
both to abound and to suffer in need.
I can do all things through Christ, which strengtheneth me.
I don't have time to get there, but just know that is one of the most out of
context scriptures ever quoted, ever, ever, ever, that
is not to put, you know, score a touchdown, that is not to
get a promotion, that is not to be able to do all these things.
What that means is, I can do all things through Christ who strengthens me.
Therefore, if I don't, or if I do.
If I have or have not, God, I can do all things because you're my strength.
Y'all with me this morning?
Notwithstanding, verse 14, you have done,
well done, that she did communicate with my affliction.
Now, ye Philippians know also that in
the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no
church communicated with me as concerning giving and receiving,
but you only.
For even in Thessalonica, you
sent once and again unto my necessity.
Not because I desire a gift, but I desire fruit
here that may abound to your account.
But I have all and abound.
I am full, having received the effort, for ditis, the
things which were sent from you, an odor of a sweet smell, a
sacrifice acceptable, well pleasing to God.
But my God shall supply all your need according to
the riches in glory by Christ Jesus.
Now unto God, and our Father, be glory forever, and ever, amen.
And salute every saint in Christ, Jesus, the brethren,
which are with me, greet you, all the saints, salute you, chiefly they
that are of Caesar's household.
The grace of our Lord, Jesus Christ, be with you all.
Amen.
You say, what does this have to do with Lydia?
What does this have to do with us today?
Remember, the church in Philippi,
the 1st convert was Lydia.
They gathered in Lydia's home.
Could it be that Lydia
was so generous in her giving, that the culture
of the church in Philippi more than any other church
at that time was generosity and giving?
providing for
the magnification of ministry.
She understood
something that Christians need to know today.
Too many Christians have been blessed by God with financial success,
and they don't understand why.
Do not let anyone tell you that God does not desire
certain folks to be wealthy.
This lie that you can't be wealthy,
that you can't be successful, that you have to be poor to love Jesus, that's not true.
Now, is it difficult to lead someone who's
rich and made it in the world to Christ?
The Bible says yes.
Why?
Because they've got what all they need.
They've done it right.
But listen, I can tell you this.
God will bless certain people in abundance.
Why?
So they can bless others in abundance as well.
Lydia was that kind of person.
She didn't she didn't see her business.
She didn't see her wealth as a way to bless herself.
She said, you know what?
Because I have received Christ, because the gospel has been
shared, because I now know Jesus, because now I
have brothers and sisters in Christ, we're going to make sure that we're generous here.
I was talking to a pastor.
And we talk about budget
and he's really, he has a good mind for it and I just don't.
So I want to glean from his wisdom and stuff and how
to build budget and where to put what there and this and that, all the things.
I'm still learning church.
But you know what?
He said, I said, man, I just wish we had, I wish we had maybe
some money like y'all do.
That's what I said, and preachers don't like when I say that to them, but you know, sometimes I say it.
And he said, you know what, it's funny?
He said, we didn't always have this.
He said, but God saved
some certain businessmen and businesswomen.
And they got on fire for Christ.
And since they've been our church saved.
And since they've continued in their faithfulness, I
will have you know their businesses have blown up in blessing.
I,
I, I don't know what else to say, but praise God.
See,
Lydia did not separate the two.
Her wealth was for the benefit of ministry, but also for the church.
She used her gift of business and know
how to successfully magnify the ministry.
Her money was not primarily for secular goals, but rather eternal investments.
This is giving with vision.
This is generosity that builds,
this is the cheerfulness Paul speaks of in 2 Corinthians 9, verse 7.
Every man according as he has purposeth in his heart, so let
him give, not grudgingly or of necessity, for
God loveth a cheerful giver.
This is never meant to give the justification
of less giving, but rather generous giving.
Everyone has expected a
give, some are even gifted in generosity.
I wonder how I wonder what impact could be made if we saw these
gifts and obedience come together for the sake of Christ.