Never forget why you are the church.
I want you to turn your Bibles to Romans chapter 12 this morning.
Romans chapter 12.
We continue breaking down the grace gifts, the spiritual
gifts that Paul lines out in Romans 12.
I want to make a point of clarification here.
I do not believe this is necessarily an
exhaustive list, but rather indicate some of
the ways the Holy Spirit can manifest the
grace of God within us in the church.
I'm not saying that there are an abundant of
other unknown gifts out there yet to be discovered,
but what I am saying is exactly what Paul says
in Romans 12, verse 4 and 5.
It says, for as we have many members in one body and all
members have not the same office.
So we, being many,
are one body in Christ, and everyone members
one of another.
I need you to hear this because we're
going to be going over these gifts in the next couple weeks.
If your gift does not contribute
to the unity of the church, you are not operating
by the Holy Spirit or the grace of God.
I need you.
I need us to realize this giftedness does not make you better,
does not make you a higher rank than any other believer.
Here's why.
The grace gift that I'm using right here in this moment, I did not earn.
It was given.
The same grace gift that you have that you're
serving with the church today.
You did not earn it.
You were given that grace gift.
Guess what?
The same grace that we have was given by the same Savior
that we have, and that's Jesus Christ.
I'm no better than you.
You know better than me.
We're just serving the king together.
Amen.
That's what it's all about.
Now, this is a great list.
I don't want to undermine the list that we're going to be going over, but
I do believe that some people can say, well, I don't have any of
these, so I guess I'm off the hook.
No, no, no, no, no.
Grace, the grace of God that you have received has
gifted you for the benefit of those around you.
Remember, there are 4 primary texts involving grace gifts.
Romans 12
right here we're talking about.
First Corinthians 12, Ephesians chapter 4,
although if I had to put a little note there, it seems that that particular
list is more offices rather than
gifts, although each office requires gifts.
And then also 1st Peter chapter 4.
We're going to touch on most of these texts throughout this portion
of study, but we will primarily be in verses
6 through 8 and Romans 12.
So if you're there this morning, I need you to say, read.
It says this.
having then gifts differing according to the grace that
is given to us, whether prophecy led us
prophesy according to the proportion of faith, or ministry
that is serving, let us wait on our ministering or serving,
or he that teacheth on teaching, or
he that exhorteth on exhortation.
He that giveth, let him do it with simplicity, he that ruleth with
diligence, he that showeth mercy with cheerfulness.
We're looking at the impact, the gospel,
in ministry, the impact of the gospel, in ministry.
Father, we thank you, Lord, for this morning.
God, we thank you for this morning.
Lord, I pray God that as
I preach your word, I do so with
power, clarity, and liberty.
God
we are gathered together.
according to your word, to hear from your word.
so that we can live out your word, therefore to share your word.
So be with us today.
Since Jesus ain't pray.
Anybody said?
Amen and amen.
Again, last week we looked at 2 gifts.
We look at the gift of prophecy and the gift of service.
What is the gift of prophecy, right?
If we believe that necessarily the office of
prophet is no longer needed, then what is the gift of prophecy?
It is an inspired utterance.
It is important to know that this gift is primarily
a proclamation gift rather than
a prediction gift.
Now, I am not saying that believers with this gift
are not able to discern current patterns
and events and cultures and share what could be to come.
But it has to be according to God's word.
For example, there are preachers from the past that
called in almost just supernatural
clarity and accuracy, what is happening right now?
Listen, that's not necessarily them being the office
of a prophet, but they are using the gift of prophecy to
speak God's word, to speak the sermon,
to the people.
Now, here's I want to give you an example of incorrect prophecy.
This is an example of what
it looks like to someone saying they have the gift of prophecy,
but they are lying to you.
Anyone at any time, in any way.
predicting the exact day of the coming of the Lord.
Whenever you hear that, whenever
someone says that, I don't care how good their intentions are.
I don't care how persuasive they are.
I don't care how many dots they connect in the world.
They are lying to you.
It is not from God.
God said, hey, we got to be ready because we don't know the day nor the hour.
So we have to understand that we got to be careful of
people saying, I've got a word from God.
Listen, if it's not from God, then it can't be from God.
You understand what I'm saying?
It's that simple.
This is not a word from God when people do this.
It's a way to get people's attention for personal benefit, period, every single time.
You know what they usually do when they're wrong?
They just make another date.
And people dig right into it.
Let me just tell you something.
Hey, we don't have to know exactly, by the way, on Wednesday
night, we're studying eschatology.
was studying how the fact that we don't know everything about the end times.
We could be very, very near, and I do believe that we are.
Some people believe that we're in it right now.
It doesn't matter.
What I'm trying to say is we have to be ready, sober minded,
steadfast, and diligent in the faith, because we don't know.
But we better be ready.
Are y'all with me this morning?
But again, according to Thayer's Greek lexicon,
the word refers to discourse emanating from divine inspiration
and declaring the purposes of God.
By the way, you can find that here.
Whether by reproving and admonishing the
wicked or comforting the afflicted or revealing things hidden, especially
by foretelling future events.
Again, we don't need that last part because we have the
completed Word of God.
If God wanted us to know all the details, he would have included them.
So we move on from the gift of prophecy,
and we see the gift of service is one that we should all be utilizing in some way.
This one is open ended regarding its specific function.
I gave some examples last week, and I want to give another one this week.
We had six baptisms last week.
We had one baptism this morning.
Somebody say amen, praise God.
You know what my part is in that?
Showing up, putting on waiters, getting the
ba- and doing the fun part.
That is my part in baptisms here at
Cedar Grow Baptist Church.
I show up.
I'm going to show up anyway, so that's not very hard.
Amen?
I go back there.
Listen, literally, everything's lined out.
But here's what people usually do not see.
They see the dunking of the folks.
They see me putting my hand up and saying all the
cool things, and, man, it's just an amazing moment, but what they don't
see is the baptistry has to be filled on Friday, so it's warm on Sunday.
They don't see that towels had to be lined out
and for each person, robes had to be distributed.
The baptistry had to be drained and cleaned.
Pictures had to be taken.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
These are people serving within the grace of God
that has been given to them.
Just because we don't see what people are
doing doesn't mean they're not serving the Lord.
Amen?
Yet we love to focus on the big gift of who we
actually are able to see, do the public work, yet without the behind the
scenes, folks serving by the grace of God, it could not happen.
It just simply could not happen.
I thank God for that diversity of gifts.
This morning, we will roll right along and look
at the gift of teaching.
Look at Romans 12, verse seven.
He says, or he that teacheth.
on teaching
Now, what is interesting about this gift
is that as mentioned in all 4 texts regarding
grace gifts.
The only variation that
might someone could say, well, that's not really teaching is found in
1st Peter chapter 4, verse 10 and 11.
He says, if any man speak, let him speak as the oracles of God.
Now, here's the thing.
This term speak is an overall term to talk and
speak, but it is the emphasis that follows
that relates this to teaching.
Again, if any man speak, let him speak as
the oracles of God.
What are the oracles of God?
What is God telling us to speak?
It's the sayings and words of God.
In other words, it is the scripture.
It's the Bible.
If you have the gift of teaching, this gift is tied
directly to God's Word.
Now, there is nothing
more unifying to a local body of believers
than sound doctrinal teaching.
Can I say that again for you?
Because I think we missed it.
There is nothing more unifying to a local body of
believers than sound doctrinal teaching,
a church that is blessed with correct teaching all the
way from the foundation up of the
Word of God will be a church that can navigate through any conflict
or tension that arises.
Do you know what happened, and as
the last 10 or almost 10 years and the ups
and downs, the ebbs and flows of the ministry, here at Cedar
Road Baptist Church, when times I didn't know what to do?
I didn't know how to lead.
I didn't know what to say.
The one thing that I knew God had me do was keep
on preaching.
No matter if I felt like it, no matter if I was nervous
about the business meeting, no matter if I just got chewed out by
a member in my office before I'm starting to preach, no matter what
was going on, my job was to bring sound doctrinal
teaching to the people.
And guess what happened?
God blessed us with it.
You understand what I'm saying?
So listen, this is a very important gift.
How important is teaching?
Jesus, during his roughly 3 years earthly
ministry, spent much of his time doing what?
Teaching the masses and personally teaching
and training the disciples.
What's greater is the methods that he used.
He was a master teacher.
There is no greater teacher that's ever walked this earth other than Christ.
He is the greatest teacher that's ever walked the earth.
Some forms of Jesus teaching, including poetry and proverbs,
and exaggeration.
By the way, every time I tell a story about my parents.
They say, Jack, you exaggerated.
Well, guess what?
It teaches it better.
You understand what I'm saying?
It just does.
Sometimes, you know, but listen, parables and many others, right?
Metaphors, riddles, paradoxes, irony and questions.
He taught in such a way that allowed his audience
to hear and relate to what was going on.
Yes, certain times he taught, and he did so in parables.
As a matter of fact, he teaches using at least 50 different parables in the gospel.
You say, what in the world is a parable?
A parable is an earthly story with heavenly meaning.
It is a heavenly message wrapped
up in an earthly context.
But he was a dynamic teacher.
Many times the spiritual meeting was hidden from the listener
due to their hardness of heart.
But he was still a dynamic teacher.
Listen, if you have the gift of teaching, you were
employed many different ways to communicate God's word.
It kills me when I
see someone who claims this gift, yet cannot keep an audience awake for 10 minutes.
So everyone wake up, please, please.
But seriously, I mean, it
is amazing to me, and I don't want to, I don't want to
sit here and say that, listen, not all the time, all the time people are
have to be passionate.
But listen, actually, yes, they do, because we're preaching the word of God.
In other words, could you imagine standing
up here and opening the vine, living,
two-edged sword of the Word of God and being boring?
That's for Wednesday night, amen?
Some of y'all, with the eschatology, like, man, I can't handle this.
This is too much, right?
Yeah, whatever.
But seriously, think about it.
But we're preaching the everlasting, living word of God.
We ought to be excited about this.
If I ever lose my passion for
the word, I've lost much.
And I need someone to shake me awake to remind me
of what I'm doing in teaching.
God will never gift us to be boring.
If you have the grace, the grace to teach,
then you must do so with passion and drive.
Let me just tell you something.
You know why so many people don't like church because they went to a dry church?
They went to a church where the pastor
was talking about being passionate about Christ, but he wasn't so himself.
They went to a church where the people and the Sunday
school teachers were talking and saying, hey, we ought to love Jesus
more than anything else, but they didn't show it.
They didn't show the love of Christ.
Listen, when you teach, the Bible says there's
stricter judgment upon you.
You better be ready for it.
You can't just get up here and say your opinion or whatever you want.
You can't just get up here and go whatever direction you need.
We are guided and directed by the word of God.
That is through the gift of teaching.
Again, sometimes this takes practice, but you cannot learn passion.
When I 1st started preaching, listen, I didn't know nothing.
I'm talking about, I knew the gospel of Jesus Christ.
I knew that he lived, died, and rose again.
And that was enough for me at that time.
And I feel like all I did for, like, 2 years straight was just preach the gospel.
But people were getting saved.
Right?
But listen, even though I knew that I didn't know all the fancy
words of the seminary that they taught, I didn't know all
the all the different, you know, systems and this and that, what I knew, I knew.
And guess what?
I liked it.
Therefore, I preached it like I liked what I was preaching.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
Are y'all with me this morning?
Listen, how important is this gift?
Well, Jesus included it before he sent it into heaven.
We love talking about going and making disciples and baptizing,
but look what it says in Matthew 28, 18 through 20.
And Jesus came and spake unto them, saying, all power is given
unto me in heaven and earth.
Go ye therefore and teach all nations.
Baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son
of the Holy Ghost, teaching them to observe
all things whatsoever I have commanded you, and lo, I am with you
always, even unto the end of the world, amen.
Listen, we love the baptism part.
We love the disciple part, but he told us to teach them.
We have to teach.
What God has commanded us.
In Paul's writing to Timothy, he frequently emphasizes
the need for sound doctrine.
2 Timothy chapter 2, verse one and 2.
Now, therefore, my son, be strong in a grace that is in Christ Jesus.
And the things thou hast heard of me, and among many witnesses,
the same commit thou to faithful men.
Why, who shall be able to teach others also?
Notice what Timothy
is to be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus.
How is he to manifest this, to commit?
That means to entrust the teachings that he has heard from Paul to others?
Why?
So that those that he teaches can go and teach other people?
We need more teachers in the church.
And listen, we we,
we, we do this thing where we like, oh, well, a teacher has to
be well spoken, and a teacher has to be this, and a teacher has,
teachers has to be gifted in the gift of teaching.
You do understand some of
the best some of the best preachers I've ever heard, they have a stutter.
Some of the best preachers I've ever heard.
They have a hard time communicating certain things.
It takes a little bit, but you're sitting there like, I know where you're going, just go there, amen?
But when they get there, it's good.
But you know they study, you know, they love the word.
Listen, some of the best, some of the best Sunday school
teachers that I've ever had, they weren't they weren't ordained pastors.
They just loved the word of God.
And they taught it to us.
We need more teachers.
We need more men who have entrusted the word who
will teach it and invest it in other men so that more people can know God's will.
By the way, there's no way to go around this.
This is a major debate amongst churches about women's roles in teaching.
Can a woman teach men?
Well, Paul does speak to this.
I need you to know, look at 1st Timothy chapter 2, 11 through 12.
Now, listen, I understand what kind of water I'm walking on now, okay?
So we're just going to have to all see what the word says and agree with it.
Amen?
You like that?
If you don't, then just get to liking it.
Look at verse 11.
Let the woman learn in silence with all subjection,
but I suffer not a woman to teach nor to usurp authority over demand,
but to be in silence.
Now, I like the NSB 95 rendering and this better.
is what it says.
It makes it more clear.
A woman was quietly receive instruction with entire
submissiveness, but are not allowing woman to
teach or exercise authority over man, but to remain quiet.
The Bible knowledge commentary.
There's a really good description of this.
The females in the congregation should
receive instruction from the male leadership with quietness and full submission.
They should not attempt to turn the tables by clamoring for
the office of congregational teacher by grasping for authority over men.
Rather, they should literally be in quietness.
That word, translated quietness in 1st Timothy
211, and silent in verse 12 does not mean complete silence or no talking.
It is clearly used elsewhere in Acts and
2 Thessalonians to mean settle down, undisturbed, not unruly.
A different word means to be silent to say nothing, but that's not the word used here.
Can I tell you something?
If you ever go to a church and they say that a woman can't say a word, they can't
do nothing, they can just sit there and be quiet, they don't know scripture.
That's not what God's word is saying.
You have to understand what it's saying.
By the way, a lot of people say this.
Oh, well, you know, that's just contextual to the church
that was in that time or that was this.
Notice who Paul is writing this to.
Timothy, amen?
It wasn't the church of Timothy.
It was Timothy.
Now, who was Timothy?
Let's think about this for a second.
Timothy was a young man who was a pastor.
Right?
He was going out, he was going to the churches.
He was teaching the men.
He was helping firm up the churches that Paul had started and planted.
But he was a pastor.
In other words, this description, this
truth, this doctrine, this this, uh,
what Paul was telling him was not just for the church
at Corinth, was not just for the church at Ephesus.
It was a principle to be taught in the churches.
Y'all with me?
You sure?
Listen, and
people will say, what about Apollos?
If you never heard of Apollos, let me introduce you to him.
Apollos was a highly educated Jew who followed Jesus.
As a matter of fact, look what Luke writes about him.
In Acts 18, 24 through 25, and a certain Jew named
Apollos, born in Alexandria, an eloquent man, and mighty
in the scriptures, came to Ephesus.
This man was instructed in the way of the Lord and being fervid
in the spirit, he spake and taught diligently the things of the Lord,
knowing only the baptism of John.
So this man was well educated, man.
He knew his stuff, but he was limited in his knowledge.
But he was passionately teaching what he needed.
By the way, I'd be okay with that.
If you would just teach what you knew with scripture, that'd be an awesome thing, amen?
You don't have to know everything.
Listen, if when I started pastoring, if there wasn't a
man named Warren Wearsby, I'd done been fired a long time ago, right?
I was leaning on other men to help me teach the scripture.
Well, he was strong.
He was a passionate teacher, still talking about Apollos.
Yet he had a limited knowledge of the things of Jesus.
So what happened?
A husband and wife ministry team.
Priscilla and Aquila.
The Bible says taught him more accurately.
Look at Acts 18, verse 26.
And he begun to speak boldly in the synagogue.
Whom when Aquila and Priscilla had heard,
they took him unto them.
and expounded unto him the way of God more perfectly.
Church, that's awesome.
That, that, see, that's
not outside of parameters of God's will.
That's not the same thing as a woman saying, hey, I want to be a pastor.
I want to be a lead teacher of a man's class.
I want to assurp.
I know the scripture better and more.
not what we're talking about.
We're talking about a husband and wife team, seeing a person who's
passionate, but having a little bit not enough knowledge.
So, hey, come here.
Let's see how you can teach better.
And they expounded the truth to him.
What a beautiful thing, by the way.
Again, has nothing to do with organizational roles of leadership.
Teaching in a church.
Can a woman have the grace gift of teaching?
Absolutely.
But a woman just like any other believer must
operate in her gifting under the authority in revealed order of scripture.
I can tell you this, I've had a lot of teachers in my life.
I've had a lot of people pour into me.
I grew up in a church where teaching was paramount.
You know what I'm saying?
Like, that's what we did, right?
We got taught, we got taught, we got taught, we got taught, we got taught.
That's all we did, just get taught, taught, taught, taught, right?
I'm talking, and I was a part of all of it.
But I had a, and I
don't know why I should be listening, but if she does, we had vacation Bible school.
Wes, I don't know how old we were.
I think we might have been, I don't know, maybe, well, I'm a grade
ahead of you, but I might have been a junior or senior.
I know how it I was, but I was in high school.
And Miss Debbie Harris.
Uh, and she was our teacher.
And she was teaching in such a way
that for some reason, man, you could just tell the Holy Spirit was in that room, man.
Now, listen, when I was in high school, I cared
about going and playing.
Right?
And I love Jesus, but that's cool.
I wanna go play now.
You know what I'm saying?
And so again, the church that I grew up at.
It was like, man, we get so much teaching.
Can we just go play volleyball?
And so I was sitting there and she was teaching and an amazing thing happened.
Now hear me out here.
We're sitting here, a bunch of high schoolers, girls and
boys were listening to Miss Debbie Teach.
And all of a sudden it becomes time to go outside the play.
Now, on any other day, you know what we done?
Jesus name, amen.
lets go.
Right?
But you know we all did?
It was almost like no one got up.
And we looked
around, we were like, do you want to go?
And they're like, no, do you want to go?
I'm like, no, I kind of want to stay and keep on getting taught.
And we looked at Miss Debbie.
I mean, I haven't thought about this in a long time.
We said, can you teach us more?
You know what she did?
She started crying.
Because all the studying, and
all the grace that she was trying to bestow upon us was
taking effect right then and there.
Now, you old folk that
might be like, well, I haven't had a reckon a long time.
Understand the intensity of the situation.
I about to say, we missed wreck at VBS, so we could be taught more.
That's a big deal.
Kiddos, you know what I'm talking about?
Listen, why?
Because she had the gift of teaching.
This lady had the gift of
teaching.
Now, let me show you what God says about it.
By the way, a lot of people say, well, well, I don't have this where they get to teach you.
I don't want to get in front of a children's class, so I don't want to get in, you know, in front of
a women's, uh, you know, class and speak.
Well, look, every woman should be a teacher.
Look at Titus chapter 2, verse 3 and five.
The age women likewise.
Notice it doesn't put an actual number on that.
Just says those are the
more experienced, right?
The age women, okay?
Some of y'all like that, amen?
We won't put no number on it.
They be in behavior as becometh holiness.
Not false accusers, not giving them much wine.
Look what it says.
Teachers of good things that
they may teach the young women to be sober, to
love their husbands, to love their children, to
be discreet, chase, keepers at home, good, obedient to their own
husbands, that the word of God be not blasphemed.
Can I tell you where these young ladies are
learning how to be wise from the world?
That's why their marriages are ending.
or right now are continuing in disaster.
You know why?
Because the church has backed up and said, well, come to church, we'll do our thing, we'll leave.
Don't worry about a thing.
The Bible says that the age women ought to teach the
young women how to live godly.
Are y'all with me?
We need less women
competing for positions.
God called men to.
And more women teaching the younger women what it looks like to be God.
By the way, listen, hey, there's been times even here at this church.
We've gotten irritated because a woman did something.
But the reason why the woman had to do it is because no man stepped up.
Are y'all with me today?
What I'm trying to say is this.
God's word's gotta be done.
Now, now, according to God's word, I'm not saying we
get out of correct doctrine and correct theology and have order.
But what I'm saying is, listen, hey, we can sit here and say, oh, well,
a woman can't do this, a woman can't do that.
All right, then, men step up.
We start doing it.
Man, y'all are not getting that this morning.
So let's get back to where we were.
Paul continues in 2nd Timothy chapter 2.
Remind them of these things, and Saul me, charge them,
and he's talking to Timothy here in the presence of God not to wrangle
about words, which is useless and leads to the ruin of the hearers,
be diligent to present yourselves, approved to
God as a workman who does not need to be ashamed, accurately handling
the word of truth.
That word handling means to teach.
Literally, it means to teach correctly, to
guide on the right path.
2nd Timothy chapter 3, verse 16 through 17.
All scriptures inspired by God and profitable for what?
Teaching.
Free proof, for correction, for training and righteousness,
so that the man of God may be adequate, equipped for every good work.
Do you know why, you know what?
The biggest problem facing our church is today, the present church.
I know we like to say
sin, and we like to say this when I say that, and listen, that is a
symptom of the problem.
The biggest problem that we have in
our church is today is biblical illiteracy.
You understand what I'm saying?
We don't know what we believe.
Because we refuse to study what we believe.
We have teachers that are not teaching
us correctly.
There are so many churches that are out there right now.
that they're getting more opinion and social activism
than God's word.
Can I tell you something?
I am not a social activist here.
I'm not here to be on any side.
I'm not here to say what you should and shouldn't do outside of God's
word and what he said you should and should not do.
I'm here to tell you that Jesus said, if you love him, you'll keep his commandments.
Therefore, we need to know his commandments.
Therefore we need sound teaching.
But biblical illiteracy is taking
over, plaguing the churches worldwide.
Dr. Albert Moeller published an article back in 2016 about this.
I'm going to read you a little excerpt
of this article because it's very troubling.
It says this.
Researchers George Gallup and Jim Castelli
put the problem squarely.
Americans revere the Bible.
But by and large, they don't read it.
And because they don't read it, they have
become a nation of biblical illiterates.
How bad is it?
Researchers tell us that it's worse than we could even imagine.
Fewer than half of all adults can name the 4 gospels.
Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John.
Amen?
Say it with me.
Cedar goes ahead of the curb, baby.
That's what I'm talking about.
All right?
Many Christians cannot identify more
than 2 or 3 of the disciples.
According to data from the Barner Research
Group, 60% of Americans can't name
even 5 of the Ten Commandments.
No wonder we're living, breaking them all.
Listen, they don't know what they are.
George Barter, president affirmed, said the bottom line,
increasingly, America is biblically illiterate.
Multiple surveys reveal the problem in stark terms.
According to 82% of Americans,
God helps those who help themselves is
a certified Bible verse.
You won't find that in here.
Those identified as born
again Christians did better by one%.
That means that people who professed
Christ, who professed Noah's words, thinks that scripture
reads, literally as a verse in scripture that says, God
helps those who helps themselves.
No wonder they're going and living their life for their own selves.
And majority
of adults think the Bible teaches that most the most important purpose
of life is taking care of one's family.
Jesus didn't teach that.
As a
matter of fact, he said, my families are those who do the Father's will.
Some
of the statistics are enough to perplex even those aware of the problem.
A barn or pole indicated that at least 12% of adults believe
that Joan of Joan of Arc was Noah's wife.
I mean, that's dumb, y'all.
I mean, wow.
ARC, ARK, what we doing here?
Another survey of graduating
high school seniors, high school seniors, those that are about to go into adult
adulthood into the church.
Joe, sadly, you can make fun of me saying that later, okay?
This is what I say. 50% thought
that Sodom and Gomorrah were husband and wife.
Maybe
that's why homosexuality's taking over our students.
A considerable number of respondents to
one point indicated that the Sermon on the Mount was preached by Billy Graham.
We are in big trouble.
That was in 2016.
You think it's gotten better?
You know what's happened
since 2016, more increasingly?
over the past 10 years, social media.
Now you don't have
to go to a church to hear false teaching.
You can just, it's in your algorithm.
May I echo the last portion
of that article clipping, we are in trouble.
Not only are we not
getting sound teaching, but much of the teaching we are getting, is false.
Do you not realize that the warning against false
teaching is emphasized and mention more than any other single theme in the New Testament?
Most of 2nd Peter is dedicated this warning.
Jude, although short, is all about the dangers of false teaching.
John repeatedly mentions false teachers.
May I make a point here,
I want you to remember, emphasizing the truth is a variation of warning against the false.
Paul uses this tactic, especially
in Timothy and Titus.
Listen, you don't study counterfeit money to know what counterfeit money is.
You study real money, so when a counterfeit comes into your hand.
You know that's not real.
Listen, we got too many people trying to study all
the wrong things, and they're neglecting the truth.
Therefore, they believe anything and everything that they hear.
People say, well, I believe I need to know about all the different religions.
Listen, if you're mature in your faith,
Hey, do some deep study.
But a new believer, or a
maybe like an elementary believer.
You don't need to study the Quran.
You don't need to study the book of Enoch.
You don't need to study all these things.
You need to study God's word so you can know what's true.
So that when the something that comes that's
not true, the Holy Spirit just kind of, hey, that's not right.
Why?
Because this is what is right.
Are y'all with me?
So how do we combat the church's biblical illiteracy?
How do we navigate this time of an abundance of false teaching?
I'm going to say this with all the love and authority I have through God's word.
Many of our most influential modern churches and
ministries are being led by false teachers scratching the itching
ears of sinful, false converts.
And if there are true converts within their influence,
those believers are drying up on the vine.
We need teachers.
Gifted men and women of God operating
in their biblical role of teaching.
You don't need a pulpit to teach.
You don't need a class to teach.
You don't even need a national podcast to teach.
Those things help greatly, but sound teaching goes beyond all that.
All you need is a conversation and a listening ear.
You need a passion for God's word, a drive to
reveal the mysteries in God's word, the discipline, to know God's
word, and the grace to teach God's word.
By the way, if you want to teach, you better study.
Let me say that again.
If you want to teach you better study.
His Bible is too deep not to be prepared.
Could you imagine jumping in the in a deep end?
without knowing how to swim.
You're gonna do what?
Drown.
I can tell you one thing.
One of my recurring nightmares is getting up in this pool.
I kid you not, and drowning in the text, not knowing what I'm
about to say, or losing her.
Listen, it scares me to not be prepared.
Why?
Because I'm gonna incur stricter judgment.
Are y'all with me this morning?
Why am I having to keep on asking you if you are or not?
This
is the only gift that is mentioned in all 4 texts.
we need it.
Do you have the gift of teaching?
If so, who are you teaching?
Older man.
By the way, I know we didn't talk about it, but in that same text, it talks about the older man teaching the younger man.
Older men, are you teaching a younger man how it is to be godly?
Or you just making fun of their generation?
It's
funny how we get onto people for sinning differently than we do.
Oh, I never did that.
What did you do?
Guarantee if I talked to you long enough, I could find out.
I guarantee you it could qualify as sin.
So instead
of looking down upon the younger generation.
Instead of looking down upon those who simply are just trying,
who simply desire to learn more, how about we teach them?
You know what I'm very careful
on when students come in with a question, not to treat them like that was a dumb question.
I will say this.
I don't believe the
same, there are no dumb questions.
There are some dumb questions, y'all.
Okay, like, I'm like, let's not be too spiritual here.
But in regards of scripture, hey, there are no dumb questions.
We need to teach.
So,
Orderman, who are you teaching?
What are you teaching?
Older women.
Again, there's no number.
Who you teaching?
What are you teaching?
We need this gift.
Life
group leaders, are you are you teaching within the grace gift of teaching?
Are you studying the show thyself approved?
Listen, I know there's preachers that like to get up here and just go off the cuff.
Can I tell you something?
There might be a time for that.
And if I ever get an opportunity and I wasn't prepared.
I want to take that opportunity no matter what, but my job is not to
come up here, just give you an opinion because I'm feeling all good.
No, my job is to have been studied and show myself,
approve the Word of God so that I can teach the Word of God.
That's what a teacher is.
Do we have any teachers in the house?
It has been eyes closed all over this place.